The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Today's topic
is factor modeling,
and the subject here basically
exploits multivariate analysis
in statistics to financial
markets where our concern is
using factors to model
returns and variances,
covariances, correlations.
And with these models,
there are two basic cases.
There's one where the
factors are observable.
Those can be
macroeconomic factors.
They can be fundamental
factors on assets or securities
that might explain
returns and covariances.
A second class of models
is where these factors
are hidden or latent.
And statistical
factor models are then
used to specify these models.
In particular, there
are two methodologies.
There's factor analysis and
principal components analysis,
which we'll get into some
detail during the lecture.
So let's proceed to talk about
the setup for a linear factor
model.
We have m assets, or
instruments, or indexes
whose values correspond to a
multivariate stochastic process
we're modeling.
And we have n time periods t.
And with the factor model
we model the t-th value
for the i-th object-- whether
it's a stock price, futures
price, currency-- as a
linear function of factors
f_1 through f_k.
So there's basically
like a state-space model
for the value of the
stochastic process,
as it depends on these
underlying factors.
And the dependence is given
by coefficients beta_1
through beta_k, which are
depending upon i, the asset.
So we allow each asset, say
if we're thinking of stocks,
to depend on factors
in different ways.
If a certain underlying
factor changes in value,
the beta corresponds to the
impact of that underlying
factor.
So we have common factors.
Now these common factors
f, this is really
going to be a nice model if the
number of factors that we're
using is relatively small.
So the number k
of common factors
is generally very, very
small relative to m.
And if you think about modeling,
say asset-- equity asset
returns in a market, there
can be hundreds and thousands
of securities.
And so in terms of modeling
those returns and covariances,
what we're trying to
do is characterize
those in terms of a modest
number of underlying factors
which simplifies
the problem greatly.
The vectors beta_i are
termed the factor loadings
of an asset.
And the epsilon_(i,t)'s are
a specific factor of asset i,
period t.
So in factor modeling,
we talk about there
being common factors affecting
the dynamics of the system,
and the factor associated
with particular cases
are the specific factors.
So this setup is
really very familiar.
It just looks like a standard
sort of regression type model
that we've seen before.
And so let's see how
this can be set up
as a set of cross-sectional
regressions.
So now we're going to fix
the period t, the time t,
and consider the
m-variate x variable
as satisfying a regression model
with intercept given by alphas.
And then the independent
variables matrix
is B, given by the coefficients
of the factor loadings.
And then we have the residuals
epsilon_t for the m assets.
So the cross-sectional
terminology
means we're fixing time
and looking across all
the assets for one fixed time.
And we're trying to explain
how, say, the returns of assets
are varying depending upon
the underlying factors.
And so the-- well OK, what's
random in this process?
Well certainly the residual
term is considered to be random.
That's basically
going to be assumed
to be white noise with mean 0.
There's going to be possibly
a covariance matrix psi.
And it's going to
be uncorrelated
across different
time cross sections.
Let's see if I can move the
mouse, if this is what's
causing the problem down here.
So in this model we have the
realizations on the underlying
factors being random variables.
The returns on the assets depend
on the underlying factors.
Those are going to be assumed
to have some mean, mu_f,
and some covariance matrix.
And basically the
dimension of that
covariance matrix omega_f
is going to be k by k.
So in terms of modeling this
problem, we go from an m
by m system of
covariances, correlations,
to focusing initially on an a
k by k system of covariances
and correlations between
the underlying factors.
Psi is a diagonal matrix
with the specific variances
of the underlying assets.
So we have basically epsilon--
the covariance matrix
of the epsilons is
a diagonal matrix,
and the covariance matrix of
f is given by this omega_f.
Well, with those
specifications we
can get the covariance
for the overall vector
of the m-variate
stochastic process.
And we have this model here
for the conditional moments.
Basically, the
conditional expectation
of the process given
the underlying factors
is this linear model in terms
of the underlying factors f.
And the covariance matrix is the
psi matrix, which is diagonal.
And the unconditional
moments are
obtained by just taking
the expectations of these.
Well actually, the unconditional
expectation of x is this.
The unconditional
covariance of x
is actually equal
to the expectation
of this plus the variance of
the conditional expectation,
or the covariance of the
conditional expectation.
So one of the formulas that's
important to realize here
is that if we're considering
the covariance of x_t, which
is equal to covariance of B
f_t plus epsilon_t, that's
equal to the covariance of
B f_t plus the covariance
of epsilon_t plus
twice the covariance
between this term and this,
but those are uncorrelated.
And so this is equal to B
covariance of f_t B transpose
plus psi.
With m assets, how
many parameters
are in the covariance
matrix if there's
no constraints on the
covariance matrix?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: How many parameters?
Right.
So this is sigma.
So the number of
parameters in sigma.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: m plus what?
PROFESSOR: OK, this is
a square matrix, m by m.
So there's possibly m
squared, but it's symmetric.
So we're double-counting
off the diagonal.
So it's m times m plus 1 over 2.
How many parameters do we
have with the factor model?
So if we think of a--
let's call this sigma star.
The number of parameters
in sigma star is what?
Well, B is an m by k matrix.
This is m by k, so we have
possibly m times k values.
The f_x is-- or the
covariance of f_t
is the number of elements in
the covariance matrix of f,
which is k by k.
And then we have psi, which
is a diagonal of dimension m.
So depending on how
we structure things,
we can have many, many fewer
parameters in this factor model
than in the unconstrained case.
And we're going to see
that we can actually
reduce this number in the
covariance matrix of f
dramatically because
of flexibility
in choosing those factors.
Well let's also look at the
interpretation of the factor
model as a series of
time series regressions.
You remember when we talked
about multivariate regression
a few lectures ago, we
talked about cross-sectional
regressions and time
series regressions,
and looking at the collection
of all the regressions
in a multivariate
regression setting.
Here we can do the same thing.
In contrast to the
cross-sectional regression
where we're fixing time and
looking at all the assets,
here we're looking at fixing
the asset i and the regression
over time for that single asset.
So the values of x_i,
ranging from time 1
up to time capital T, basically
follows a regression model
that's equal to the intercept
alpha_i plus this matrix F
times beta_i, where beta_i
corresponds to the regression
parameters in this
regression, but they
are the factor corresponding to
an asset i on the different k
factors.
In this setting, the covariance
matrix of the epsilon_i vector
is the diagonal matrix sigma
squared times the identity.
And so this is the classic
Gauss-Markov assumptions
for a single linear
regression model.
Well, as we did previously,
we can group together
all of these time series
regressions for all the m
assets together by simply
putting them all together.
So we start off with x_i
equal to basically F beta_i
plus epsilon_i.
And we can basically
consider x_1, x_2, up to x_n.
So we have a T by m
matrix for the m assets.
And that's equal to a regression
model given by basically
what's on the slides here.
So basically, we're able to
group everything together
and deal with everything all
at once, which computationally
is applied in fitting these.
Let's look at the simplest
example of a factor model.
This is the single-factor
model of Sharpe.
We went through the capital
asset pricing model,
how returns on assets and
stocks are basically--
the excess return on
stock can be modeled
in terms as a linear
regression on the excess return
of the market.
And the regression
parameter beta_i
corresponds to the level of
risk associated with the asset.
And all we're doing
in this model is,
by choosing different
assets we're choosing assets
with different levels of
risk scaled by the beta_i.
And they may have
returns that vary
across assets given by alpha_i.
The covariance
matrix of the assets
has-- the unconditional
covariance matrix
has this structure.
It's basically equal to the
variance of the market times
beta beta prime plus psi.
And so that equation
is really very simple.
It's really self-evident from
what we've discussed, but let
me just highlight what it is.
Sigma squared beta beta
transposed plus psi.
And that's equal
to sigma squared
times basically a column vector
of all the betas, beta_1 down
to beta_m times its transpose
plus a diagonal matrix
with the psi.
So this is really a very,
very simple structure
for the covariance.
And if you had wanted to
apply this model to thousands
of securities, it's
basically no problem.
You can construct a
covariance matrix.
And if this were appropriate
for a large collection
of securities, then the
amount-- the reduction
in terms of what you're
estimating is enormous.
Rather than estimating
each cross-correlation
and covariance of
all the assets,
the factor model tells us what
those cross covariances are.
So that's really where the
power of the model comes in.
And in terms of why
is this so useful,
well in portfolio management
one of the key drivers
of asset allocation is
the covariance matrix
of the assets.
So if you have an
effective model
for modeling the
covariance, then that
simplifies the portfolio
allocation problem
because you can specify
a covariance matrix
that you are confident with.
And also in risk
management, effective models
of risk management
deal with, how
do we anticipate what would
happen if different scenarios
occur in the market?
Well, the different
scenarios that can occur
can be associated with what's
happening to underlying factors
that affect the system.
And so we can consider
risk management approaches
that vary these underlying
factors, and look at
how that has an impact
on the covariance matrix
very directly.
Estimation of Sharpe's
single index model.
We went through
before how we estimate
the alphas and the betas.
In terms of estimating
the sigmas--
the specific
variances-- basically,
that comes from the
simple regression as well.
Basically, the sum of the
squared estimated residuals
divided by t minus 2.
Here we're assuming unbiasedness
because we have two parameters
estimated per model.
Then for the market
portfolio, that basically
has a simple estimate as well.
The psi hat matrix would
just be the diagonal
of that-- the diagonal of
the specific variances.
And then the unconditional
covariance matrix
is estimated by simply plugging
in these parameter estimates.
So, very simple and effective
if that single-factor
model is appropriate.
Now needless to say,
a single-factor model
doesn't characterize the
structure of the covariances
and/or the returns typically.
And so we want to consider
more general models,
multi-factor models.
And the first set of models
we're going to talk about
are common factor variables
that can actually be observed.
Basically any factor
that you can observe
is a potential candidate
for being a relevant factor
in a linear factor model.
The effectiveness of
a potential factor
is determined by
fitting the model
and seeing how much
contribution that factor
makes to the explanation
of the returns
and the covariance structure.
Chen, Ross, and Roll wrote
a classic paper in 1986.
Now Ross is actually
here at MIT.
And with their paper,
they looked at modeling--
rather than looking
at these factors
directly, including
those in the model,
they looked at
transforming these factors
into surprise factors.
So rather than having
interest rates just
as a simple factor directly
plugged into the model,
it would be the change
in interest rates.
And additionally, not only just
the change in interest rate,
but the unanticipated
change in interest
rates given market information.
So their paper goes
through modeling different
macroeconomic variables with
vector autoregression models,
and then using those to
specify unanticipated changes
in these underlying factors.
And so that's where
the power comes in.
And that highlights how when
you're applying these models,
it does involve some
creativity to get the most bang
for the buck with your models.
And the idea they had of
incorporating unanticipated
changes was really
a very good one
and is applied quite widely now.
Now with this setup,
one basically--
if one has empirical data over
times 1 through capital T,
then if one wants to
specify these models,
one has their observations
on the x_i process.
You basically have observed
all the returns historically.
We also, because the
factors are observable,
have the F matrix as a
set of observed variables.
So we can basically use those to
estimate the beta_i's and also
estimate the variances
of the residual terms
with simple regression methods.
So implementing these
is quite feasible,
and basically applies methods
that we have from before.
So what this slide now discusses
is how we basically estimate
the underlying parameters.
We need to be a little bit
careful about the Gauss-Markov
assumptions.
You'll remember that if we
have a regression model where
the residual terms are
uncorrelated and constant
variance, then the
simple linear regression
estimates are the best ones.
If there is unequal
variances of the residuals,
and maybe even
covariances, then we
need to use generalized
least squares.
So the notes go through those
computations and the formulas,
which are just simple extensions
of our regression model theory
that we had in
previous lectures.
Let me go through an example.
With common factor
variables that
are using either fundamental
or asset-specific attributes,
there's the approach of-- well,
it's called the BARRA Approach.
This is from Barr Rosenberg.
Actually, I have to say, he
was one of the inspirations
to me for going into statistical
modeling and finance.
He was a professor at UC
Berkeley who left academics
very early to basically
apply models in trade money.
As an anecdote, his
current situation
is a little different.
I'll let you look that up.
But anyway, this
approach basically
provided the BARRA Approach
for factor modeling and risk
analysis, which is still
used extensively today.
So with common factor
variables using
asset-specific
attributes-- in fact,
the factor realizations
are unobserved
but are estimated in the
application of these models.
So let's see how that goes.
Oh, OK, this slide talks about
the Fama-French approach, which
concerns-- OK, Fama and
French, Fama of course
we talked about him
in the last lecture.
He got the Nobel
Prize for his work
in modeling asset price
returns and market efficiency.
Fama and French
found that there were
some very important
factors affecting
asset returns in equities.
Basically, returns
tended to vary depending
upon the size of firms.
So if you consider small
firms versus large firms,
small firms tended to
have returns that were
more similar to each other.
Large firms tended to
have returns that were
more similar to each other.
So there's basically a
big versus small factor
that is operating in the market.
Sometimes the market
prefers small stocks,
sometimes it prefers
large stocks.
And similarly,
there's another factor
which is value versus growth.
Basically, stocks that
are considered good values
are stocks which are cheap,
basically, for what they have.
So you're basically getting
a stock at a discount
if you're getting a good value.
And value stocks can be
measured by looking at the price
to book equity.
If that's low, then
the price you're
paying for that equity in the
firm is low, and it's cheap.
And that compares
with stocks for which
the price relative to the
book value is very, very high.
Why are people willing
to pay a lot for stocks?
In that case, well it's
because the growth prospects
of those stocks is high,
and there's an anticipation
basically that the
current price is just
reflecting a projection of how
much growth potential there is.
Now the Fama French approach
is for each of these factors
to basically rank order all
the stocks by this factor
and divide them
up into quintiles.
So say this is market cap.
We can divide up all the
stocks in-- basically
consider a histogram,
or whatever,
of all the market caps of all
the stocks in our universe.
And then divide it up into
basically the bottom fifth,
the next fifth, and
then-- it probably
needs to go up-- the top fifth.
And the Fama-French
approach says, well,
let's look at an equal-weighted
average of the top fifth.
And basically, buy that
and sell the bottom fifth.
And so that would be the
big versus small market
factor of Fama and French.
Now, if you look at
their work, they actually
do the bottom minus the
top, because the value
tends to outperform the other.
So they have a factor
whose more positive
values and associated
more generally
with positive returns.
But that factor can
be applied and used
to correlate with individual
asset returns as well.
Now, with the BARRA
Industry Factor--
this is just getting back
to the BARRA Approach--
the simplest case
of understanding
the BARRA industry
factor models is
to consider looking
at dividing stocks up
into different industry groups.
So we might expect that,
say oil stocks will
tend to move together and
have greater variability
or common variability.
And that could be very different
from utility stocks, which
tend to actually be
quite low-risk stocks.
Utility companies
are companies which
are very highly regulated.
And the profitability
of those firms
is basically overlooked
by the regulators.
They don't want the
utilities to gouge consumers
and make too much profit from
delivering power to customers.
So utilities tend to have
fairly low volatility
but very consistent
returns, which
are based on reasonable,
from a regulatory standpoint,
levels of profitability
for those companies.
Well with an industry
factor model, what we can do
is associate factor
loadings, which basically
are loading each asset in
terms of which industry group
it's in.
So we actually know the beta
values for these stocks,
but we don't know
the underlying factor
realizations for these stocks.
But in terms of the
betas, with these factors
we can basically get a well
defined beta vectors and B
matrix for all the stocks.
And the problem
then is, how do we
specify the realization
of the underlying factors?
Well the realization of
the underlying factors
basically is just estimated
with a regression model.
And so if we have all of our
assets x_i for different times
t, those would have a model
given by factor realizations
corresponding to the k industry
groups with known beta_(i,j)
values.
And the estimation of
these, we basically
have a simple
regression model where
the realizations of
the factor returns f_t
are given by essentially
a regression coefficient
in this regression, where
we have the asset returns
x_t, the known
factor loadings B,
the unknown factor
realizations f_t.
And just plugging
into the regression,
if we do it very simply
we get this expression
for f hat t, which is the
simple linear regression model
estimating those realizations.
Now this particular estimate
of the factor realizations
is assuming that the variability
of the components of x
have the same variance.
This is like the
linear regression
estimates under normal
Gauss-Markov assumptions.
But basically the
epsilon_i's will
vary across the
different assets.
The different assets will
have different variabilities,
different specific variances.
So that's actually going
to be heteroscedasticity
in these models.
So this particular vector
of industry averages
should actually be extended
to accommodate for that.
So we have the estimation
of the covariance matrix
of the factors can
then be estimated
using these estimates
of the realizations.
And our estimation of the
residual covariance matrix
can then be estimated.
So I guess an initial estimate
of the covariance matrix sigma
hat is given by this known
matrix B times our sample
estimate of the factor
realizations plus the diagonal
matrix C hat.
And a second step
in this process
can incorporate
information about there
being heteroscedasticity along
the diagonal of the psi's
to adjust the
regression estimates.
So we basically get a
refinement of the estimates
that does account for the
non-constant variability.
Now this property of
heteroscedasticity verses
homoscedasticity in estimating
the regression parameters,
it may seem like
this is a nicety
of the statistical theory that
we just have to try and check,
but it's not too big a deal.
But let me highlight where this
issue comes up again and again.
With portfolio optimization,
we went through last time--
for mean-variance
optimization, we
want to consider a weighting of
assets that basically weights
the assets by the expected
returns, pre-multiplied
by the inverse of the
covariance matrix.
And so we basically in
portfolio allocation
want to allocate to
assets with high return,
but we're going to penalize
those with high variance.
And so the impact of discounting
values with high variability
arises in asset allocation.
And then of course arises
in statistical estimation.
Basically with signals
with high noise,
you want to normalize
by the level of noise
before you incorporate the
impact of that variable
on the particular model.
So here are just some notes
about the inefficiency
of estimates due to
heteroscedasticity.
We can apply generalized
least squares.
A second bullet here is
that factor realizations
can be scaled to represent
factor mimicking portfolios.
Now with the
Fama-French factors,
where we have say big
versus small stocks or value
versus growth
stocks, it would be
nice to know, well what's
the real value of trading
that factor?
If you were to have unit
weight to trading that factor,
would you make money or not?
Or under what periods
would you make money?
And the notion of factor
mimicking portfolios
is important.
Let's go back to the
specification of the factor
realizations here.
f hat t, the t-th realization
of the factors, their k factors,
is given by essentially
the regression estimate
of those factors from the
realizations of the asset
returns.
And if we're doing
this in the proper way,
we'd be correcting for
the heteroscedasticity.
Well this realization
of the factor returns
is a weighted average or
a weighted sum of the x_t.
So we have basically f_t
is equal to a matrix times
x_t, where this is B B prime
toe the minus one, B prime.
So our k-dimensional
realizations-- let's see,
this is basically k by 1.
Each of these k factors is
a weighted sum of these x's.
Now the x's, if these are
returns on the underlying
assets, then we can consider
normalizing these factors.
Or basically normalizing
this matrix here
so that the row weights sum to
1, say, for a unit of capital.
So if we were to invest
a net unit of one capital
unit in these assets, then
this factor realization
would give us the return on
a portfolio of the assets
that is perfectly correlated
with the factor realization.
So factor mimicking portfolios
can be defined that way.
And they have a
good interpretation
in terms of the realization
of potential investments.
So let's go back.
The next subject is
statistical factor models.
This is the case where
we begin the analysis
with just our collection of
outcomes for the process x_t.
So basically our
time series of asset
returns for m assets
over T time units.
And we have no clue initially
what the underlying factors
are, but we hypothesize
that there are factors that
do characterize the returns.
And factor analysis and
principal components analysis
provide ways of uncovering
those underlying factors
and defining them in terms
of the data themselves.
So we'll first talk
about factor analysis.
Then we'll turn to principal
components analysis.
Both of these
methods are efforts
to model the covariance matrix.
And the underlying covariance
matrix for the assets x
can be estimated with sample
data in terms of the sample
covariance matrix.
So here I've just written
out in matrix form
how that would be computed.
And so with this m by T
matrix x, we basically
take that matrix, take
out the means by computing
the means with multiplying
by this matrix,
and then take the
sum of deviations
about the means for
all the m assets
individually and
across each other,
and divide that by capital T.
Now, the setup for
statistical factor models
is exactly the same as
before, except the only thing
that we observe is x_t.
So we're hypothesizing a
model where alpha is basically
a vector that is basically
the vector of mean returns
of the individual assets.
B is a matrix of factor
loadings on k factors f_t.
And epsilon_t is white
noise with mean 0,
covariance matrix
given by the diagonal.
So the setup here is the
same basic setup as before,
but we don't have the
matrix B or the vector f_t.
Or, of course, alpha.
Now in this setup,
it's important
that there is an
indeterminacy of this model,
because for any given
specification of the matrix B
or the factors f, we can
actually transform those
by a k by k invertible
matrix H. So for a given
specification of this model,
if we transform the underlying
factor realizations f by the
matrix H, which is k by k,
then if we transform the
factor loadings B by H inverse,
we get the same model.
So there is an indeterminacy
here, or a-- OK,
there's an indeterminacy of
these particular variables,
but there's basically
flexibility in how
we define the factor model.
So in trying to uncover a factor
model with statistical factor
analysis, there is
some flexibility
in defining our factors.
We can arbitrarily
transform the factors
by an invertible
transformation in the k space.
And I guess it's important
to note that what changes
when we do that transformation?
Well the linear
function stays the same
in terms of the covariance
matrix of the underlying
factors.
Well, if we have a covariance
matrix for those underlying
factors, we need to accommodate
the matrix transformation
H in that.
So that has an impact there.
But one of the
things we can do is
consider trying to
define a matrix H, that
diagonalizes the factors.
So in some settings, it's useful
to consider factor models where
you have uncorrelated
factor components.
And it's possible to
define linear factor
models with uncorrelated factor
components by a choice of H.
So with any linear
factor model in fact,
we can have uncorrelated factor
components if that's useful.
So this first bullet
highlights that point
that we can get
orthonormal factors.
And we can also have
zero mean factors
by adjusting the
data to incorporate
the mean of these factors.
And if we make these
particular assumptions,
then the model does
simplify to just
being the covariance matrix
sigma_x is the factor
loadings B times its transpose
plus a diagonal matrix.
And just to reiterate,
the power of this
is basically no matter how
large m is, as m increases
the B matrix just increases
by k for every increment in m.
And we also have an additional
diagonal entry on the psi.
So as we add more and more
assets to our modeling,
the complexity basically
doesn't increase very much.
With all of our statistical
models, one of the questions
is how do we specify the
particular parameters?
Maximum likelihood estimation is
the first thing to go through,
and with normal
linear factor models
we have normal
distributions for all
the underlying random variables.
So the residuals
epsilon_t are independent
and identically distributed,
multivariate normal dimension m
with diagonal matrix psi given
by the individual elements'
variances.
f_t, the realization
of the factors,
the k-dimensional
factors can have mean 0,
and just to have the
identity covariance
we can scale them and
make them uncorrelated.
And then x_t will be
normally distributed
with mean alpha and
covariance matrix
sigma_x given by the formulas
in the previous slide.
With these assumptions,
we can write down
the model likelihood.
The model likelihood
is the joint density
of our data given the
unknown parameters.
And the standard setup actually
for statistical factor modeling
is to assume
independence over time.
Now we know that there can
be time series dependence.
We won't deal with
that at this point.
Let's just assume that they
are independent across time.
Then we can consider this
as simply the product
of the conditional density
of x_t given alpha and sigma,
which has this form.
This form for the density
function of a multivariate
normal should be very
familiar to you at this point.
It's basically the extension
of the univariate normal
distribution to m-variate.
So we have 1 over the square
root of pi to the m power.
There are m components.
And then we divide by the square
root of the individual variance
or the determinant of
the covariance matrix.
And then the exponential
of this term here,
which for the t-th case is
a quadratic form in the x's.
So this multivariate normal
x, we take off its mean
and look at the quadratic
form of that with the inverse
of its covariance matrix.
So there's the
log-likelihood function.
It reduces to this form here.
And maximum likelihood
estimation methods
can be applied to specify all
the parameters of B and psi.
And there's an EM algorithm,
which is applied in this case.
I think I may have
highlighted it before,
but the EM algorithm is a very
powerful estimation methodology
for maximum likelihood
in statistics.
When one has very
complicated models which
can be simplified-- well,
models that are complicated
by the fact that we have
hidden variables-- basically
the hidden variables lead
to very complex likelihood
functions.
A simplification
of the EM algorithm
is that if we could observe
some of the hidden variables,
then our likelihood
functions are very simple
and can be computed directly.
And the EM algorithm
alternates estimating
the hidden variables, assuming
the hidden variables are known
doing the simple estimates with
the observed hidden variables,
and then estimating the
hidden variables again,
and just iterating that
process again and again.
And it converges.
And their paper
demonstrates that this
applies in many, many
different application settings.
And it's just a very, very
powerful estimation methodology
that is applied here with
statistical factor analysis.
I indicated that for now we
could just assume independence
over time of the data points
in computing its likelihood.
You recall our discussion
a couple of lectures back
about the state-space models,
linear state-space models.
Essentially, that linear
state-space model framework
can be applied here as
well to incorporate time
dependence in the data as well.
So that simplification is not
binding in terms of holding us
up in estimating these models.
Let me go back here, OK.
So the maximum likelihood
estimation process
will give us estimates of the
B matrix and the psi matrix.
So applying this EM
algorithm, a good computer
can actually get estimates of
B and psi and the underlying
alpha, of course.
Now from these we can estimate
the factor realizations f_t.
And these can be estimated by
simply this regression formula,
using our estimates for
the factor loadings B
hat, our estimates of
alpha, we can actually
estimate the factor
realizations.
So with statistical
factor analysis,
we use the EM algorithm to
estimate the covariance matrix
parameters.
Then the next step, we
can estimate the factor
realizations.
So as the output
from factor analysis,
we can work with these
factor realizations.
And those realizations
or those estimates
of the realizations
of the factors
can then be used basically
for risk modeling as well.
So we could do a statistical
factor analysis of returns
in, say, the
commodities markets.
And identify what factors are
driving returns and covariances
in commodity markets.
We can then get estimates
of those underlying
factors from the methodology.
We could then use those
as inputs to other models.
Certain stocks may depend
on significant factors
in the commodity markets.
And what they depend on, well
we can use statistical modeling
to identify where
the dependencies are.
So getting these realizations
of the statistical factors
is very useful, not
only to understand
what happened in the
past with the process
and how these
underlying factors vary,
but you can also use those
as inputs to other models.
Finally, let's see,
there was a lot
of interest with
statistical factor
analysis on the interpretation
of the underlying factors.
Of course, in terms
of using any model,
it's once confidence
rises when you have
highly interpretable results.
One of the initial applications
of statistical factor analysis
was in measuring IQ.
And how many people here
have taken an IQ test?
Probably everybody
or almost everybody?
Well actually if you want to
work for some hedge funds,
you'll have to
take some IQ tests.
But basically in an IQ test
there are 20, 30, 40 questions.
And they're trying to
measure different aspects
of your ability.
And statistical
factor analysis has
been used to try and understand
what are the underlying
dimensions of intelligence.
And one has the
flexibility of considering
different transformations
of any given
set of estimated factors by this
H matrix for transformation.
And so there has been work in
statistical factor analysis
to find rotations of
the factor loadings
that make the factors
more interpretable.
So I just raise that as there's
potential to get insight
into these underlying factors
if that's appropriate.
In the IQ setting, the
effort was actually
to try and find what
are interpretations
of different dimensions
of intelligence?
We previously talked about
factor mimicking portfolios.
The same thing applies.
One final thing is with
likelihood ratio tests,
one can test for whether
the linear factor model is
a good description of the data.
And so with likelihood
ratio tests,
we compare the
likelihood of the data
where we fit our unknown
parameters, the mean vector
alpha and covariance matrix
sigma, without any constraints.
And then we compare that
to the likelihood function
under the factor model
with, say, k factors.
And the likelihood
ratio tests are
computed by looking at twice the
difference in log likelihoods.
If you take an advanced
course in statistics,
you'll see that basically this
difference in the likelihood
functions under many conditions
is approximately a chi
squared random
variable with degrees
of freedom equal to the
difference in parameters
under the two models.
So that's why it's
specified this way.
But anyway, one can test for
the dimensionality of the factor
model.
Before going into an
example of factor modeling,
I want to cover principal
components analysis.
Actually, principal
components analysis
comes up in factor
modeling, but it's also
a methodology that's appropriate
for modeling multivariate data
and considering
dimensionality reduction.
You're dealing with data
in very many dimensions.
You're wondering is there
a simple characterization
of the multivariate
structure that lies
in a smaller dimensional space?
And principle components
analysis gives us that.
The theoretical framework for
principal components analysis
is to consider an
m-variate random variable.
So this is like a single
realization of asset returns
in a given time, which has
some mean and covariance matrix
sigma.
The principal
components analysis
is going to exploit the
eigenvalues and eigenvectors
of the covariance matrix.
Choongbum went through
eigenvalues and singular value
decompositions.
So here we basically have
the eigenvalue/eigenvector
decomposition of our
covariance matrix sigma, which
is the scalar eigenvalues
times the eigenvector
gamma_i times its transpose.
So we actually are able to
decompose our covariance matrix
with eigenvalues, eigenvectors.
The principal
component variables
are to consider taking away the
mean from the random vector x,
alpha.
And then consider the weighted
average of those de-meaned x's
given by the i-th eigenvector.
So these are going to be
called the principal component
variables, where gamma_1 is
the first one corresponding
to the largest eigenvalue.
Gamma m is going to be the
m-th, or last, corresponding
to the smallest.
The properties of these
principal component variables
is that they have mean 0,
and their covariance matrix
is given by the diagonal
matrix of eigenvalues.
So the principal
component variables
are a very simple sort
of affine transformation
of the original variable x.
We translate x to a new origin,
basically to the 0 origin,
by subtracting the means off it.
And then we multiply
that de-meaned x value
by an orthogonal
matrix gamma prime.
And what does that do?
That simply rotates
the coordinate axes.
So what we're doing is creating
a new coordinate system
for our data, which
hasn't changed
the relative position of the
data or the random variable
at all in the space.
Basically, it just is using
a new coordinate system
with no change in the
overall variability of what
we're working with.
In matrix form, we can express
this principal component
variables p.
Let's consider partitioning
p into the first k
elements and the last
m minus k elements p_2.
Then our original random vector
x has this decomposition.
And we can think of this
as being approximately
a linear factor model.
We can consider from
principal components analysis
essentially if p_1, the
principle component variables,
correspond to our factors,
then our linear factor model
would have B as given by
gamma_1, F as given by p_1.
And our epsilon vector would
be given by gamma_2 p_2.
So the principal
components decomposition
is almost a linear factor model.
The only issue is this
gamma_2 p_2 is an m-vector,
but it may not have a
diagonal covariance matrix.
Under the linear factor model
with a given set of factors
k less than m, we
always are assuming
that the residual vector
has covariance matrix
equal to a diagonal.
With a principal
components analysis,
that may or may not be true.
So this is like an
approximate factor model,
but that's why this is called
principal components analysis.
It's not called principal
factor analysis yet.
The empirical principal
components analysis now.
We've gone through
just a description
of theoretical principal
components, where
if we have a mean vector alpha,
covariance matrix sigma, how
we would define these
principle component variables.
If we just have sample
data, then this slide
goes through the computations
of the empirical principal
components results.
So all we're doing is
substituting in estimates
of the means and
covariance matrix,
and computing the
eigenvalue/eigenvector
decomposition of that.
And we get sample principal
component variables
which are-- we basically
compute x, the de-meaned vector,
or matrix of realizations and
pre-multiply that by gamma hat
prime, which is the
matrix of eigenvectors
corresponding to the
eigenvalue/eigenvector
decomposition of the
sample covariance matrix.
This slide goes through the
singular value decomposition.
You don't have to go through and
compute variances, covariances
to derive estimates of the
principal component variables.
You can work simply with the
singular value decomposition.
I'll let you go through
that on your own.
There's an alternate definition
of the principal component
variable though
that's very important.
If we consider a
linear combination
of the components of x, x_1
through x_m, given by w,
if we consider a linear
combination of that which
maximizes the variability
of that linear combination
subject to the norm of the
coefficients w equals 1,
then this is the first
principal component variable.
So if we have in two
dimensions the x_1 and x_2,
if we have points that look like
an ellipsoidal distribution,
this would correspond to having
alpha 1 there, alpha 2 there,
a sort of degree of variability.
The principal
components analysis
says, let's shift to the origin
being at (alpha_1, alpha_2).
And then let's rotate the axes
to align with the eigenvectors.
Well the first principal
component variable
finds the dimension at which
the coordinate axis at which
the variability is a maximum.
And basically along
this dimension
here, this is where
the variability
would be the maximum.
And that's the first
principal component variable.
So this principal
components analysis
is identifying
essentially where's
there the most
variability in the data,
where it's the most variability
without doing any change
in the scaling of the data?
All we're doing is
shifting and rotating.
Then the second principal
component variable
is basically the
direction which is
orthogonal to the first, which
has the maximum variance.
And continuing that
process to define all
m principal component variables.
In principal
components analysis,
there's discussions of the
total variability of the data
and how well that's explained
by principal components.
If we have a covariance
matrix sigma,
the total variance
can be defined
and is defined as the sum
of the diagonal entries.
So it's the trace of
a covariance matrix.
We'll call that the total
variance of this multivariate
x.
That is equal to the sum
of the eigenvalues as well.
So we have a decomposition
of the total variability
into the variability of
different principal component
variables.
And the principal
component variables
themselves are uncorrelated.
You remember the
covariance matrix
of the principal
component variables
was the lambda, the diagonal
matrix of eigenvalues.
So the off-diagonal
entries are 0.
So the principal
component variables
are uncorrelated, and
have variability lambda_k,
and basically decompose
the variability.
So principal components
analysis provides
this very nice
decomposition of the data
into different
dimensions, with highest
to lowest information content
as given by the eigenvalues.
I want to go
through a case study
here of doing factor modeling
with the U.S. Treasury yields.
I loaded in data into R, which
ranged from the beginning
of 2000 to the end of May 2013.
And here are the yields on
constant maturity U.S. Treasury
securities ranging from
3 months, 6 months,
up to 20 years.
So this is essentially
the term structure
of US Government [INAUDIBLE]
of varying levels of risk.
Here's a plot of [INAUDIBLE]
over that period.
So starting in the
[INAUDIBLE], we
can see this, the rather
dramatic evolution of the term
structure over
this entire period.
If we wanted to have
set any [INAUDIBLE].
If we wanted to do a principal
components analysis of this,
well if we did the
entire period we'd
be measuring variability
of all kinds of things.
When things go down, up, down.
What I've done in this
note is just initially
to look at the period
from 2001 up through 2005.
So we have five years of data
on basically the early part
of this period that I
want to focus on and do
a principal components analysis
of the yields on this data.
So here's basically the series
over that five year period.
Beginning of this
analysis, this analysis
is on the actual yield changes.
So just as we might be modeling
say asset prices over time
and then doing an analysis
of the changes, the returns,
here we're looking
at yield changes.
So first, you can see
there's-- basically,
the average daily value for the
different yield tenors ranging
from 3 months up to 20, those
are actually all negative.
That corresponds to the time
series over that five year
period.
Basically the time series
were all at lower levels
from beginning to
end on average.
The daily volatility is the
daily standard deviation.
Those vary from
0.0384 up to .0698
for-- is that the three year?
And this is the standard
deviation of daily yield
changes where 1 is like 1%.
And so basically it's
between three and six basis
points a day are the variation
in the yield changes.
So that's something
that's reasonable.
When you look at the
news or a newspaper
and see how interest
rates change from one day
to the next, it's generally
a few basis points
from one day to the next.
This next matrix is
the correlation matrix
of the yield changes.
If you look at
this closely, which
you can when you
download these results,
you'll see that
near the diagonal
the values are very high, like
above 90% for correlation.
And as you move across,
away from the diagonal,
the correlations
get lower and lower.
Mathematically that
is what is happening.
We can look at these things
graphically, which I always
like to do.
Here is just a graph, a bar
chart of the yield changes
and the standard
deviations of the yield
changes, daily volatilities
ranging from very short yields
to long-tenor yields,
up to 20 years.
So there's variability there.
Here is a pairs
plot of the data.
So what I've done is
just looked at basically
for every single tenor, this
is say the 5 year, 7 year,
10 year, 20 year.
I basically plotted
the yield changes
of each of those
against each other.
We could do this with basically
all nine different tenors,
and we'd have a very dense
page of a pairs plot.
So I split it up
into looking just
at the top and bottom
block diagonals.
But you can see basically
how the correlation
between these yield
changes is very tight
and then gets less tight
as you move further away.
With the long
tenors-- let's see,
the short tenors--
one, one more.
Here the short tenors, ranging
from 3 year, 2 year, 1 year,
6 month, and so forth.
So here you can see how it
gets less and less correlated
as you move away
from a given tenor.
Well the principal
components analysis
gives us-- if you conduct
a principal components,
basically the standard
output is first
a table of how the
variability of the series
is broken down across the
different component variables.
And so there's
basically the importance
of components for each of
the nine component variables
where it's measured in terms
of the relative squared
standard deviations of these
variables relative to the sum.
And the proportion
of variance explained
by the first component
variable is 0.849.
So basically 85% of
the total variability
is explained by the first
principal component variable.
Looking at the second
row, second in, 0.0919,
that's the percentage
of total variability
explained by the second
principal component variable.
So 9%.
And then for third
it's around 3%.
And it just goes
down closer to 0,
There's a scree plot for
principal components analysis,
which is just a plot
of the variability
of the different principal
component variables.
So you can see whether
the principal components
is explaining much variability
in the first few components
or not.
Here there's a huge
amount of variability
explained by the first
principal component variable.
I've plotted here the
standard deviations
of the original yield
changes in green,
versus the standard deviations
of the principal component
variables in blue.
So we basically are modeling
with principal component
variables most of
the variability
in the first few
principal components.
Now let's look at
the interpretation
of the principal
component variables.
There's the loadings
matrix, which
is the gamma matrix for the
principal components variables.
Looking at numbers is
less informative for me
than looking at graphs.
Here's a plot of the loadings
on the different yield
changes for the first
principal component variable.
So the first principal
component variable
is a weighted average of
all the yield changes,
giving greatest weight
to the five year.
What's that?
Well that's just a measure of a
level shift in the yield curve.
It's like, what's
the average yield
change across the whole range?
So that's what the first
principal component
variable is measuring.
The second principal component
variable gives positive weight
to the long tenors, negative
weight to the short tenors.
So it's looking at the
difference between the yield
changes on the long
tenors verses the yield
change on the short tenors.
So that's looking at how the
spread in yields is changing.
Then the third principal
component variable
has this structure.
And this structure
for the weights
is like a double difference.
It's looking at the difference
between the long tenor
and medium tenor,
minus the medium tenor,
minus the short tenor.
So that's giving us a measure
of the curvature of the term
structure and how that's
changing over time.
So these principal
component variables
are measuring the level
shift for the first,
the spread for the second, and
the curvature for the third.
With principal
components analysis,
many times I think
people focus just
on the first few principal
component variables and then
say they're done.
The last principle component
variable, and the last few,
can be very, very
interesting as well,
because these are the variables
of the original scales,
the linear combinations which
have the least variability.
And if you look at the
ninth principle component
variable-- there were
nine yield changes
here-- it's basically looking
at a weighted average of the 5
and 10 year minus the 7 year.
So this is like the hedge of the
7 year yield with the 5 and 10
year.
So that difference
in yield change
is-- that combination
of yield change
is going to have the
least variability.
The principal
component variables
have zero correlation.
Here's just a pairs plot of the
first three principal component
variables and the ninth.
And you can see
that those have been
transformed to have zero
correlations with each other.
One can plot the cumulative
principal component variables
over time to see how the
evolution of these underlying
factors has changed
over the time period.
And you'll recall that
we talked about the first
being the level shift.
Basically from 2001 to 2005, the
overall level of interest rates
went down and then went up.
And this is captured by this
first principal component
variable accumulating from 0
down to minus 8, back up to 0.
And the scale of this
change from 0 to minus 8
is the amount of
greatest variability.
The second principal
component variable
accumulates from 0 up to
less than 6, back down to 0.
So this is a measure
of the spread
between long and short rates.
So the spread
increased, and then it
decreased over the period.
And then the curvature, it
varies from 0 down to minus 1.5
back up to 0.
So how the curvature changed
over this entire period
was much, much less, which
is perhaps as it should be.
But these graphs
indicate basically
how these underlying factors
evolved over the time period.
In the case note I go through
and fit a statistical factor
analysis model to
these same data
and look at identifying
the number of factors.
And also comparing the results
over this five year period
with the period
from 2009 to 2013,
and comparing those
different results.
They are different,
and so it really
matters over what period one
specifies these models to.
And fitting these models is
really just a starting point
where you want to
ultimately model
the dynamics in these
factors and their structural
relationships.
So we'll finish there.